How are you, children?
We are doing fine!
You may sit.
Thank you, teacher!
Let's start on three!
One, two, three.
Lotus flowers...
Silence!
...are blossoming...
...I am happy.
You might think
there's no use of singing the Smot.
That's not true!
We have to learn it together attentively.
Smot is important to everyone.
It changes our behavior,
educates our speech and soul,
so that we would be polite.
We have to respect one another!
Therefore we have to learn carefully
and remember it together.
Smot is an important song
that teaches us to respect the elderly,
our parents and relatives.
If we think about it carefully,
we are going to understand
the real meaning of it.
"Parents are our first teachers" -
have we learned that song already?
Not yet!
- Not yet?
"Parents are our first teachers"
is very educational.
Would you like me to sing it for you?
Parents are our very first teachers.
They are the best teachers in the world.
One might say that
they are the real Theravada.
My name is Suon Srey Oun.
I am 35 years old.
I am a farmer
and a dharma chant (Smot) teacher.
When I was young, I used to listen
people chanting at the funerals.
Smot is very important to me.
It makes me happy.
It gives my life meaning.
Buddhist dharma is all I have.
Dharma makes people
considerable  towards one another.
Although we have Smot, people still
don't know how to respect each other.
This does not help
our country to develop.
Again! One, two three...
I am the oldest of my sisters.
That's why I need to help
my parents to make a living.
I have had a very rough life
since my childhood.
I am not totally free.
She carries water, collects the firewood,
cooks, cleans, feeds the cows.
She does everything.
She helps us with all the chores
at the times she is not teaching.
When my children were small,
we use to carry water
to the vegetables 50-70 times per day.
Now we are old and ill
from all the overworking.
We struggled a lot. My life got
better when my children grew up.
We provide 9 long carpets, 20 big carpets
and 40 carpets for the monks.
Also materials, decorations,
drinks and 2 days of service.
I don't make a profit from it.
It is for gasoline only.
My name is Pheun Srey Pov.
People also know me as Srey Pov Smot,
because I sing Smot
at different ceremonies.
I think I was the first one
to create such a business.
Old people always help each other
organize the ceremonies.
They have never thought
about earning a living from it.
For me, singing Smot
doesn't have a price.
If I had some kind of office job,
I couldn't sing Smot.
Your lips are so pale!
So pale. So pale.
I used to be just a regular girl,
a simple Smot singer.
At school, I learned general knowledge
and English, like other children.
Now I have a permanent job
at the Buddhist sector.
I am recognized by Buddhist people
and by people, I have worked for.
There is a big difference since
I was supported by my parents
and the organization.
Now I make my own living and
offer jobs to younger generation.
Mother feels relieved,
even if she is unhappy and tired.
Mother feels better.
Now, both of you together.
Teacher, please lead us!
I feel for the mother.
It sounds so sad,
I cannot sing it now.
Under the rain and thunder...
No, you're confused -
please repeat!
We went to visit
our grandparents and relatives.
My teacher makes me laugh,
I cannot sing Smot now.
I smile because I'm satisfied now.
You can sing Smot very well.
My teacher knows my weakness.
I can't sing Smot when you laugh.
I am just really happy!
Students who want to become
the masters or teachers,
need to be focused and patient.
If they are not committed,
they won't be able to make it
because Smot is complicated.
I know Smot since I was
because my father used to sing Smot.
I started to learn from him.
The history of Smot started when
Buddha compiled a teaching for us.
When I was 17, the Pol Pot regime
started and Smot was not allowed.
They banned it completely,
we had to whisper Smot.
I practiced Smot whispering
so that nobody would hear.
If they had heard us singing Smot,
they would have captured us.
They didn't care whether
it was a night or day.
They would have caught
and killed us immediately.
After Pol Pot, joyful times began.
There was no more sadness.
We were freed from Pol Pot
and Buddhism returned.
People and Buddha followers
were all happy.
I was confident enough to
start singing Smot again.
I was afraid that the Khmer
culture would fade away.
I tried to teach the younger generation
so they could teach the next generation.
I wanted to make sure
that our culture wouldn't be lost -
that's why I made an effort.
I taught almost 10 years.
8 out of 10 students were successful.
If they had the skills like
Srey Oun and Srey Pov do.
After I retired, I
assigned Srey Oun to teach.
She now has a job
because I taught her.
Dharma is the blessing sound
of success.
The golden discipline
has the highest value.
Praying is like the golden silk.
When I was learning to chant Smot,
I was offered a scholarship.
I wanted to move to Phnom Penh
to become a traditional singer.
I listened to beautiful songs by
Sin Sisamuth and Ros Sereysothea.
I wished I could sing
just like them.
I like to sing
but I don't dare dream too big
because I don't have
the education for it.
Our living conditions
and family  status weren't very good.
There was nobody
to  help out our parents.
After failing
the  9th grade final exam,
I quit school to
help my parents.
Our children work in a factory and give
away their salary to support the family.
We live a much better life now compared
to the past when the children were young.
If I had continued studying
I would   have a better life like others.
Young girls in my village get
married at the age of 17 to 18.
I will be 36 this year and
soon I will be 40 years old.
If I do get married, then hopefully
to a normal man, because I'm not pretty.
I want a man with a good personality,
I don't care about the looks.
I would be satisfied with a good personality
because I'm not pretty either.
I am so worried about
my daughter's future.
If she doesn't get married,
I hope that her nephew
is going to take care of her.
I don't want my daughters
to go far away from me.
I'm afraid that they'll have
problems with the in-laws.
It is going to be good,
if her husband believes in her,
but what if he listens to his mother?
I have seen daughters living with
their in-laws and having problems.
Sometimes they come back crying.
I don't know what the future brings.
If I am going to get married or not.
If not, I need my nephew
to live with me.
I believe in Karma.
If I do a lot of good,
my nephews will grow up fine.
When I get old,
they take care of me
as their biological mother.
In Cambodia, parents always
worry about their daughters.
When the daughter grows up,
they always fix her up with a man.
Normally they get married at the age
of 18 or 19 and have children.
Some of my friends are married
and   their children go to school already.
After graduating from college,
I wanted to be successful at my work.
When I got 25, my parents started
talking to me about marriage.
I asked for more time
to be independent.
I want to stay single,
independent and happy.
If I get married I would soon
be tied up with children.
I don't want that at the moment.
Luckily my parents understand me.
I can stay single
without any pressure.
I would like to ask the
whole family to gather here.
We are starting with the "Asking for
parents' forgiveness" ceremony.
Madams, have you already
prepared new clothes for her?
These are already here?
I am going to prepare these.
Madam, you should also
prepare some money.
You can relax now.
Are you ok?
Please help her!
Let her stand up slowly by herself.
Before we start chanting
the Buddhist dharma song.
I would like to pay respect
to the Three Jewels.
Special respect to the ceremony owners
and all the Buddhism followers.
Please accept this dharma chanting as
a  respect of our our parents' good deeds.
I bow down in respect and
raise my hands to ask for forgiveness.
I am asking forgiveness for everything
I have done wrong since I was young.
My body and mind ache because of
all my careless words,
ignorance and stubbornness.
Because of all my inappropriate behavior.
I feel enlightenment and
I am starting to understand now.
I am forever grateful to you.
Mother, father, I feel dolors.
Since I was born you have worried
about me and taken care of me.
It is time to ask for forgiveness
from your mother.
Speak out from your mind.
Please express your respect,
gratitude and love.
The truth is hidden
in the words of children.
We would like to ask for forgiveness
on behalf of all the grandchildren.
We wish that you live
a healthy and long life.
We love you so much!
Respecting parents is something
that is always on my mind.
I don't need a big ceremony
to express that.
I always bring good news
and results to my parents.
Since I was young,
whether in high school or in college,
I have never failed an exam.
I never disappoint them.
This woman is mature.
She loves traditions.
How many young women are
interested in things like that?
Only her!
She can manage the monks, gifts,
monks' places, everything.
I now ask for your forgiveness.
For all I have done
to you, my parents.
For all my careless words.
Parents, please forgive me!
Mother and father do a lot of good.
I offer my body and words.
And bow down to express my respect.
This song reminds me of the day
I celebrated a ceremony for my mother.
I started to sing this song,
but couldn't finish it,
because I started crying.
It reminds me of the mistakes
I have made concerning my parents.
I celebrated the ceremony
and chanted this song...
...I started crying
already during the first paragraph.
I haven't had many
happy moments in my life.
I have been working very hard
since childhood.
Living together with my whole family
is my happiness.
I am going to stay here forever
and take care of them with respect.
Nowadays, everybody lives with the
purpose to keep their body alive.
Death is unpredictable.
No one can escape from it.
That's why we sing Smot to people
to make them think about it.
After we die,
we are like a piece of firewood.
Only our soul flies away from the body.
Our body is like a house
where the soul stays.
When the soul leaves,
the house burns down
a nd the soul flies away
to find a new house.
If you are a good person,
you go to heaven.
If they are bad,
they go deep into the Earth.
Inside the Earth,
they become evil demons.
This is according to the Cambodian belief
as well as the Buddhist belief.
Eight big Jewel places.
Praised by all kinds of animals.
The first Jewel is the quiet Lumbini park.
That's where Buddha was born.
The second is the place
of enlightenment.
Under the Jewel fig tree.
The third is the place...
...where Buddha taught Dharma...
...to the five monks.